Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ק"ד, kuf daled,
104. We pick
up ק"ה, kuf hey, is it?
No, no, we pick up on ק"ד עמוד ב'. kuf daled amud
bet.
No, we pick up on ק"ג עמוד ב'. kuf gimmel amud bet.
Okay, we pick up on ק"ג עמוד ב'. kuf gimmel amud bet.
We're in the middle of some stories about the deathbed scenes or
the end-of-life scenes of רבי, Rebbe, and the most recent one was
where he
appointed as the
ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva חנינא בר חמא. Chanina bar Chama. So, and
some stories about that. Now the גמרא Gemara says where חנינא בר
חמא Chanina bar Chama sort of allowed רבי אפס Rabbi Apas to
take the position for a few years before him because רבי אפס
Rabbi Apas was older.
So now the גמרא Gemara has a problem with why רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina was appointed the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. So the גמרא
Gemara says, it's about ten lines before the lines get wide, right
under where it says איוב כ"ב Iyov chaf bet and there's that
quote from that פסוק. pasuk. The next line, it says the following:
והא הוי רבי חייא. Veha'avi Rabbi Chiya.
One minute, you know, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya was around. Why was
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina appointed the ראש ישיבה? Rosh Yeshiva? רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya was presumably רבי'ס Rebbe's like star תלמיד. talmid. He was
the person who edited the
תוספתא. Tosefta. Why wasn't he made the ראש ישיבה? Rosh Yeshiva? So
the גמרא Gemara says נח נפשיה. nach nafshe. No, he had already
passed away prior to רבי'ס Rebbe's death. So the גמרא Gemara says,
is that really true? והאמר רבי חייא, Ve'amar Rabbi Chiya, didn't רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya say אני ראיתי קברו של רבי, Ani ra'isi kivro
shel Rebbe, I saw the grave of רבי Rebbe וירדתי עליו דמעות
veradeti alav dmaos and I cried over it? איפכא, Ipocha, so reverse
it. It's רבי Rebbe saw the grave of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya.
והאמר רבי חייא, Ve'amar Rabbi Chiya, but we have a ברייתא braisa
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said אותו יום שמת רבי בטלה קדושה, Oso
yom shemeis Rebbe batla kedusha,
the day that רבי Rebbe died, sanctity died? איפכא, Ipocha,
okay, it was רבי Rebbe says it about רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya,
not רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said it about רבי. Rebbe. והתניא, Vehatanya,
but we have another ברייתא braisa that says כשחלה רבי, keshachala Rebbe,
when רבי Rebbe got sick, נכנס רבי חייא אצלו, nichnas Rabbi Chiya
etzlo, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya went to him ומצאו שהוא בוכה, umatzau
shehu boche, saw him crying. אמר לו, Amar lo, he says to
him, רבי, Rebbe, מפני מה אתה בוכה, mipnei ma ata boche, why
are you crying? והתניא, Vehatanya, מת מתוך השחוק, meis mitoch hasechok, if
you die out of a state of laughter and a good mood,
סימן יפה לו, siman yafe lo, it's a good sign for him.
מתוך הבכי, mitoch habchi, if you die in the midst of crying,
סימן רע לו, siman ra lo, it's a bad sign for him.
So you don't want to be dying in the middle of crying.
And then now it goes on with the rest of this ברייתא.
braisa. פניו למעלה, panav lemala,
if a person dies with his face facing upward, סימן יפה לו,
siman yafe lo, it's a good sign. למטה, lemata, סימן רע לו,
siman ra lo, face down it's a bad sign. פניו כלפי העם,
panav klapei ha'am, if he's facing the people, סימן יפה לו, siman
yafe lo, it's a good sign. כלפי הכותל, klapei hakosel, if he's
facing towards the wall away from the people, סימן רע לו, siman
ra lo, it's a bad sign. פניו ירוקין, panav yerukin, and his
face is yellow or greenish, סימן רע לו, siman ra lo, it's
a bad sign. פניו צהובין ואדומין, panav tzehubin va'adumin, if it's bright
and red, סימן יפה לו, siman yafe lo, it's a good sign.
It's interesting, here it reverses the bad, here it says the bad
before the good. Anyway, מת בערב שבת meis be'erev shabbos סימן יפה
לו, siman yafe lo, if you die on ערב שבת erev shabbos
it's a good sign because then you enter into קדושה, kedusha, you
go to עולם הבא, olam haba, you go into שבת shabbos in
עולם הבא. olam haba. במוצאי שבת bemotzaei shabbos סימן רע לו, siman
ra lo, after שבת shabbos
it's a bad sign, which is interesting, why not יחטוף yachaf another
שבת shabbos before you die anyway. מת בערב יום הכיפורים meis be'erev
yom hakippurim סימן רע לו, siman ra lo, here it's a little
bit in the reverse, a person dies on ערב יום כיפור erev
yom kippur it's a bad sign because he dies before his sins
are atoned. במוצאי יום הכיפורים bemotzaei yom hakippurim סימן יפה לו, siman
yafe lo, after יום כיפור yom kippur it's a good sign. מת
מחולי מעיים
meis
micholi
me'ayim סימן יפה לו, siman yafe lo, if he dies from digestive
whatever, digestive illnesses, so then it's a good sign. Why? מפני, mipnei,
presumably that atones for sin or something because it's so painful, I
don't know. מפני שרובן של צדיקים, mipnei sheruban shel tzaddikim, I don't
know, מפני שרובן של צדיקים מתים בחולי מעיים, mipnei sheruban shel tzaddikim
meisin becholi me'ayim, we actually know that the majority of righteous people
die from having some illness of the digestive tracts. Anyway, אמר לו,
amar lo, anyway, בקיצור, bekitzur,
why are you crying? אמר לו, amar lo, he says to them,
אנא על תורה ומצוות קבכינא, ana al torah umitzvos kavachina, I'm crying
because of all the תורה torah and מצוות mitzvos that I'm going
to be losing, which is not exactly an answer because that's why
anybody would be crying, so it would still be an issue of
סימן רע לו. siman ra lo.
Anyway, moving on. So you see that רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya was
around when רבי Rebbe died. So the גמרא Gemara says איבעית אימא
איפכא, ibayeisema ipko, let's reverse that one as well, but it's getting
a little bit, the evidence is a little piling up that רבי
Rebbe died before רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. ואיבעית אימא, ve'ibayeisema, and if
you want, here's a better answer to all those fine, רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya survived רבי Rebbe and nevertheless he was not made the
ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. Why was he not made the ראש ישיבה?
Rosh Yeshiva? לעולם לא תיפוך, le'olam lo siphach, don't reverse any of
this. רבי חייא עסיק במצוות הוה, Rabbi Chiya asa bemitzvot hava, רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya was not appointed the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva because
he devoted more time to actually going out in the world and
really doing things and doing מצוות mitzvos and not just being in
the בית מדרש beis medrash and sitting and learning, which might mean
that he wasn't the same level of the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
as חנינא בר חמא, Chanina bar Chama, or might mean that he
didn't want to be restricted to the בית מדרש beis medrash the
same way חנינא'ס Chanina's appointment to the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva would
be. Now how do you know this? עסיק במצוות הוה. asa bemitzvot
hava. Now we have a very famous גמרא. Gemara. רבי סבר לא
אפגניה, Rebbe savar lo afagnei, and רבי Rebbe thought I will not
injure him, I will not take this opportunity of מצוות mitzvos away
from him. So again, it does not sound like he wasn't at
the same level. might even have been at a greater level of
תורה Torah knowledge as רבי חנינא, Rebbe Chanina, but רבי Rebbe did
not want to deprive him by giving him the appointment of ראש
ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva of the opportunity to go out in the world
and do מצוות. mitzvahs. והיינו דכי הוו מנצי רבי חנינא ורבי חייא.
vahaynu dechi havu mintzi Rebbe Chanina veRebbe Chiya. Now רבי חנינא Rebbe
Chanina and רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya were debating, disputing, actually literally it
means fighting, not fist fighting, but whatever, fighting with their words. אמר
ליה רבי חנינא לרבי חייא. amar lei Rebbe Chanina leRebbe Chiya. So
רבי חנינא Rebbe Chanina said to רבי חייא, Rebbe Chiya, בהדי דידי
מנצית? bahadi didi minatzit? You think you're going to fight against me?
You're going to argue against me? דאם חס ושלום משתכחה תורה מישראל,
de'im chas veshalom mishtakcha Torah miYisrael, God forbid תורה Torah would be
lost from the Jewish people, מהדרנא לה מפלפולי, mehadarna lah mipilpuli,
I could restore it all just based on my, you know, sort
of פלפול, pilpul,
my intellectual analytical abilities.
So אמר ליה רבי חייא, amar lei Rebbe Chiya, רבי חייא Rebbe
Chiya said back to him, אנא עבדי דלא משתכחה תורה מישראל. ana
avdi dela mishtakcha Torah miYisrael. You think you're so brilliant, you're focused
on how smart you are that you could restore it, I will
actually go out there and make sure that it doesn't get lost
in the first place, תורה מאי עבידנא? Torah mai avidna? Torah from
self. דאייתינא כיתנא, de'aisina kitna, I will take flax ושדינא veshadina and
I will plant it, ומגדלנא ושרינא umegadalna ushrina and based on what
grows I will weave a net, וציידנא טביא, vetzaidna tavya,
I will capture a deer, ומאכילנא בישרא ליתמי umachilna bisra leyasmi
and then I will use the meat to feed the orphans, ואריכנא
מגילתא va'arichna megilta
and I will create Torah scrolls out of it, ממשכי דטביא mimishchei
detavya
from the skins of the deer, וסליקנא למתא vesalikna lemata and I'll
go to the city דלית בה מקרי דרדקי delais bah makrei dardakei
that has nobody to teach the kids like a תורה Torah teacher,
a חדר cheder teacher, וכתיבנא חמישה חומשי לחמישה ינוקי uchisivna chamisha chumshei
lechamisha yanukei
and I will write out the five scrolls of the five books
of the תורה Torah for five different kids, ומתנינא שיתא סדרי לשיתא
ינוקי umasnina shita sidrei leshita yanukei
and I would teach the six סדרי sidrei of משנה Mishnah to
six different children, one per child. ולכל חד וחד אמרי ליה, ulechol
chad vechad amrei lei,
and to each child I will say, אתני סדרך לחברך, atni sidrach
lechavrach,
you teach what you know to your friend. Okay, so everybody winds
up being both a student and a teacher and everybody winds up
teaching everybody and it distributes the responsibility so that you can have
everybody participating, you don't have to have all the weight of responsibility
on one people, but then everybody winds up in the process of,
you know, both being a learner and a teacher, a student and
a
teacher. והיינו, vahaynu, what's his name, Michael Kaplowitz was saying yesterday at
the end after the early מנין minyan that when he was young
and he went to Russia, you know, as part of these trips
they did to Russia when there were the refuseniks and he met
people who were there as the תורה Torah teachers and he said
like they barely knew anything and here they were, they were teaching
תורה Torah to others. So the Rabbi there said: You don't understand.
The way it works here is if you know אלף בית גימל,
aleph beis gimmel, then you teach to somebody else אלף בית, aleph
beis, and then he teaches to somebody else אלף. aleph. And that's
how we spread תורה. Torah. So, so this way everybody winds up,
everybody knows something and teaches something to somebody else. And, you know,
and you also have to appreciate obviously this is also a critique
of רבי חנינא, Rebbe Chanina, because רבי חנינא's Rebbe Chanina like: I
know everything, I'm going to be able to restore everything to the
whole world and it all depends on me, right? And it's all
my תורה. Torah. And here it's very much a different idea of,
you know, a distributive knowledge and it's not all about you and
you don't have to be the most brilliant person in the room
in order to be the person that's, you know, taking part of
the responsibility of owning and of sustaining תורה. Torah. More תורה, Torah,
right?
It's like, you know, he's helping the whole plant.
Well, that's the other thing. Right, exactly, exactly. That is the other
thing also and, you know, don't think that just because you're such
a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham you can't take a step out
of the בית מדרש, beis medrash, you can go out there and
do real-world things like planting a flax and capturing deer and your
responsibilities are not only in the intellectual sphere as well. They're actually
in helping provide for people. Exactly.
Okay, so that's kind of like the last lesson, like you feed
the orphans so they get one meal, you know, and once it's
gone it's gone. The scroll that you make from the hide... Uh-huh.
No, that's the point. He gives them nets also they can catch
more deer too.
Yeah,
that's a good point too.
He's not only giving them the fish, he's giving them the fishing
pole. Right. And he's and it's all right and it's much more
fully encompassing. Okay,
והיינו דאמר רבי. vahaynu de'amar Rebbe. And that's what רבי Rebbe says,
כמה גדולים מעשי חייא, kama gedolim ma'asei Chiya,
how great are the actions, are the deeds of חייא. Chiya. All
right, so very, very nice little contrast here to the ראש ישיבה
Rosh Yeshiva who's kept in his little ivory tower and it's all
about him and his תורה Torah knowledge and the person who goes
out there. And it does not seem again that the גמרא Gemara
says that he wasn't able to be the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva,
just didn't want to deprive him by giving him the appointment of
ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva of the opportunity to go out in the
world and do מצוות. mitzvahs. אמר ליה רבי שמעון בר רבי. amar
lei Rebbe Shimon bar Rebbe. Now רבי שמעון בר רבי Rebbe Shimon
bar Rebbe said, אפילו ממך? afilu mimcha?
is he to רבי, Rebbe, is רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya even greater
than you? אמר ליה אין. amar lei in. Yes, his deeds, of
course. Now Rabbi Yossi was not just the person in the in
the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. He was a נשיא. Nasi. He had
a lot of political responsibilities and so on. So are his deeds
even greater than yours? He said, yes. אמר רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי,
Amar Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yossi, so Rabbi Yishmael the son of
Rabbi Yossi said, אפילו מאבא, Afilu me-abba, even more than my father?
אמר ליה חס ושלום. Amar lei chas veshalom. לא תהא כזאת בישראל.
Lo tehei kazot be-Yisrael. No, God forbid. So I don't know what
the point is and what we're supposed to know about Rabbi Yossi
and what the point of that comparison contrast is. Anyway, so now
the גמרא Gemara goes on. That was a very beautiful story, very
powerful story, and now the גמרא Gemara says the following. אמר להו
לבני קטנא אני צריך. Amar lehu livni katana ani tzarich.
He said, I need my youngest son. Of course, we know presumably
at a different stage because he's already had his sons with him
and we've already had and, you know, his the sages with him
together with the sons. But now he just wants to speak to
his son. נכנס אצלו. Nichnas etzlo. Rabbi Shimon went. ומסר לו סדרי
חכמה. Umasar lo sidrei chochmah.
He gave him over the, you know, the tools of wisdom or
something. Somehow, some, I don't know what this is supposed to be—secret,
esoteric wisdom, or how to, how commentators say like how, you know,
he should hold himself as a sage, how he should, you know,
ways in which he should learn, ways in which he should present
himself to the larger society, something he gave over to him relating
to wisdom. אמר להו לבני גדול אני צריך. Amar lehu livni gadol
ani tzarich. I need my eldest son. נכנס רבן גמליאל אצלו. Nichnas
Rabban Gamliel etzlo. Rabban Gamliel went. Rabban Gamliel, you remember, is going
to be the נשיא. Nasi. ומסר לו סדרי נשיאות. Umasar lo sidrei
nesiyut. He gave him over some of the, you know, skills of
being a נשיא. Nasi. Again, you know, you have a feeling by
the whole way it's being told that there's some like he gave
him over the secrets, because if it's like really skills, you don't
teach somebody all the skills that they need for a job like
at the last few minutes of your life, you know? So anyway,
it's like the old joke, right, about the guy who says, put
the three
envelopes in the safe.
No, you don't know that story? Okay, anyway. All right, I'll tell
you afterwards. אמר לו—what?
Amar lo When שמעון בר יוחאי Shimon bar Yochai died, that last
stage he gave over the the final knowledge that he was allowed
to give in this world?
Oh, I don't remember that. Is that a מדרש? Midrash? Maybe, I
don't remember that.
That's part of the celebration of ל״ג בעומר.
Lag BaOmer. Oh, I mean, that might be—I don't think if that's
in the גמרא, Gemara, but it might be a later
story, I don't know. Okay. אמר לו בני נהוג נשיאותך ברמים. Amar
lo beni nehog nesiyutecha beramim. You know, practice
your your your rulership in heights, or some have
בדמים, bedamim, but anyway, whatever that means. רש״י Rashi says ברמים beramim
means שתהא יושב בין גדולים. she-tehei yoshev bein gedolim. No, you have
to assume certain positions of honor. It's necessary for you in your,
you know, to assume them even if you're not seeking them. Remember
it said before that Rabban Gamliel was the great in יראת שמים.
Yirat Shamayim.
וזרוק מרה בתלמידים. U-zerok mara be-talmidim. And make the students fearful of
you. Again, maybe even if that's not your natural inclination, you know,
you have to act in a way that's appropriate for the
office. איני והא כתיב ואת יראי ה׳ יכבד. Eini veha ketiv ve-et
yirei Hashem yechabed. And those who fear God he will honor. דאמר
מר זה יהושפט מלך יהודה. De-amar mar zeh Yehoshaphat Melech Yehudah. That
was Yehoshaphat the King of Yehuda. כשהיה רואה תלמיד חכם היה עומד
מכסאו ומחבקו ומנשקו. Keshehayah roeh talmid chacham hayah omed mikesao umichavko umenashko.
When he saw a Torah sage, he would raise up, get up
from his throne and hug him and kiss him. וקורא לו רבי
רבי מרי מרי. Vekorei lo Rabbi Rabbi Mari Mari. My master, my
master, teacher, my teacher. So you see that even a king is
supposed to show honor to the Torah sages and not sort of
emphasize his own his position over them. So the גמרא Gemara says,
yeah, but okay, it understands that it's true, you could say his
תלמידים, talmidim, תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, or your students. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, but you're right, you could have said that. לא
קשיא הא בצינעא הא בפרהסיא. Lo kashya ha betzina ha befarhesya. It's
one thing in private; in private obviously that gets back to the
יראת חטא, Yirat cheit, you know, and it's another thing in public.
In public you have to you have to own the, you know,
own the role of your office. So again, that's an interesting right
balance, which is very hard to maintain, right? That the יראת שמים
Yirat Shamayim and maintain that humility and at the same time don't
let that, you know, own your position of leadership. Okay, תניא, Tanya,
we taught in a בריתא, Beraita, רבי מוטל בציפורי. Rabbi mutal be-Tzippori.
Rabbi was sick, and he had all of these sort of deathbed
occurrences in Tzippori. ומקום מוכן לו בבית שערים. Umakom muchan lo be-Beit
She’arim. But the place that was set as designated for him to
be buried was in Beit She'arim. And they and they למעשה lema'aseh
Rabbi, you know, had moved his seat of his of his נשיאות
nesiyut to Tzippori in the final years of his life, but he
was buried and they have all of these these כוכין, kuchin, right,
these like
catacombs, sarcophagi, whatever, in Beit She'arim. That's where he had been for
many years before. Yeah, exactly, prior to the final years of his
life. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא תניא צדק צדק תרדוף הלך
אחר רבי לבית שערים. Veha tanya tzedek tzedek tirdof halach achar Rabbi
le-Beit She’arim. Go to Rabbi to Beit She'arim, so presumably he had
been living in Beit She'arim. So the גמרא Gemara says, you're right,
רבי בבית שערים הוה אלא כיון דחלש אמטיוהו לציפורי. Rabbi be-Beit She’arim
havah ella keivan de-chalash amtivuhu le-Tzippori. They brought him to Tzippori. That's
where he was, you know, once he started going downhill. דמדליא דאיירא.
Demadalya de-ayara. That it's high up so the air quality is
better. מדליא madlya that it's high up, so the air quality is
better. ובסים אוירא u-vasim avira and the air is sweeter, it's a
better, it's better for the air quality. ההוא יומא דנח נפשיה, Hahu
yoma de-nach nafshei,
that day that he died, דרבי, de-Rebbi, the Rebbi died, גזרו רבנן
תעניתא. gazru rabbanan taanita.
The Rabbis, meaning he hadn't died yet, but it was the day
that was going to be the day of his death and it
was clear that he was, you know, he was holding on to
the, you know, and it was imminent. So the Rabbis, the Torah
sages made a fast day. ובעו רחמי u-va'u rachamei and they were
praying to God. ואמרי ve-amri and they said, כל מאן דאמר נח
נפשיה דרבי, kol man de-amar nach nafshei de-Rebbi, anybody who says that
Rebbi has died, ידקר בחרב, yidaker be-charev, will be pierced with a
sword. Okay, so they're already anticipating denial that's going to come after
he dies, first stage of grief. But he hadn't died yet, but
it was clearly imminent. סליקא אמתיה
דרבי, Selika amteih de-Rebbi, so Rebbi's maidservant went up לאיגרא le-igra to
the roof. אמרה Amrah and she said, עליונים מבקשים את רבי, elyonim
mevakshim et Rebbi, the supernal realms, you know, heavens desire Rebbi's soul,
ותחתונים מבקשים את רבי, ve-tachtonim mevakshim et Rebbi,
and those down here want to keep Rebbi on this earth. יהי
רצון שיכופו תחתונים את העליונים, Yehi ratzon she-yakufu tachtonim et elyonim, may
it be thy will God that the lower realms, you know, subjugate,
meaning like, you know, win out over the upper realms and that
the prayers are accepted and that Rebbi is kept down here. כיון
דחזאי, Keivan de-chazai, now then once she saw Rebbi, כמה זימני, kama
zimnei, how many times דעייל לבית הכסא de-ayeil le-veit ha-kissei he had
to go to the bathroom, וחלץ תפילין ve-chalatz tefillin and removed his
Tefillin, ומנח להו u-manach le-hu and put it back on, וקא מצטער
ve-ka mitzta'er and how much anguish he had, and she saw how
much pain he was in. אמרה, Amrah, she said, יהי רצון שיכופו
עליונים את התחתונים, Yehi ratzon she-yakufu elyonim et ha-tachtonim, may it be
the will that the higher realms will, you know, win out over
the lower realms. Rebbi, it would be a רחמנות. rachmanus. What?
This is what Rebbi Chiya was saying, חולי מעיים
cholei me'ayim is a good thing. Well, that's a good point. Oh
yeah, you're right. You're right. It was the חולי מעיים cholei me'ayim
dying. I missed the חולי מעיים cholei me'ayim part. Thank you. Okay,
so she was actually praying that he should die, that it would
be a רחמנות rachmanus for him, you know, to pass away. ולא
הוו שתקי רבנן מלמיבעי רחמי, ve-la havu shatkei rabbanan milimeiv'ei rachamei, but
the Rabbis wouldn't stop praying, so he wasn't able to die, they
were sort of keeping his soul down here. שקלה כוזא, Shakla kuza,
she took like a little jug, ושדייא מאיגרא לארעא ve-shadya mei-igra le-ar'a
she threw it off the roof to the ground. אישתיקו Ishtiku and
they were shocked for a moment and they and they were silent
for a second מרחמי me-rachamei from their prayers. ונח נפשיה דרבי, Ve-nach
nafshei de-Rebbi, that moment Rebbi, and that moment Rebbi died. By the
way, this גמרא Gemara is used, it's an interesting גמרא Gemara because
it's used in some discussions of medical ethics, right, about like is
it do we assume that it's always better to, you know, to
hold on to every last second of life? Right? So I mean
it's not the same as, you know, as euthanasia of speeding it,
but do you have to do every single measure possible to hold
on to every second of life? Or sometimes is it just a
רחמים rachamim to let, you know, the death take its natural course?
So now, similar story.
You know the one about דוד המלך? David HaMelech? Right, right, right
about דוד
המלך
David
HaMelech wouldn't stop learning, exactly, exactly.
And מלאך המות malach ha-mavet was the one who had to do
the distraction.
Exactly, exactly. You're right, exactly.
And I hadn't thought about this, but you know Rebbi attributed his
his lineage back to דוד המלך. David HaMelech. So that might be
an intentional paralleling.
And מלאך המות malach ha-mavet wasn't sick. Right, exactly.
But there might be an intentional paralleling of those, you know, of
of of those. And it was also interesting once we're talking about
the parallels, you know, because Rebbi was both like the head political
and he was also, it's not clear actually it seems pretty clear
from the גמרא Gemara that he wasn't the the biggest sage in
the time. I mean he was the one who edited the משנה,
Mishna, but nevertheless, but you know he did have as opposed to
in בבל Bavel where the political leadership and the Torah leadership were
independent, in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, right, you had them sort of
merged. I mean here's Rebbi assigning who's also going to be the
ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. What's the נשיא Nasi doing who's assigning ראש
ישיבה? Rosh Yeshiva? So it's interesting because before it said I'm not
any greater than משה. Moshe. You're not any greater than משה. Moshe.
Remember this yesterday we're talking about like waiting thirty days before you
go back to the learning. But it created that parallel, right? So
there's that parallel to משה, Moshe, right? And then there's this parallel
here implicitly talked about him being a נשיא Nasi and it mentioned
יהושפט Yehoshaphat a minute ago, so there's this also parallel to דוד
המלך David HaMelech which might be also suggested by this story.
Did somebody go on the roof yesterday to commit suicide?
Ah yes, to commit suicide, that's true also.
Did somebody go on the roof?
You know there was a system. That's a good point. Exactly. Okay.
אמרו ליה רבנן לבר קפרא, Amru lei rabbanan le-Bar Kappara,
the Rabbis said to Bar Kappara, זיל איין, zil ayein, go see
what's happening with Rebbi. So maybe they said it after after the
thing threw off the roof and they figured something was up. אזל
אשכחיה דנח נפשיה, Azal ashkacheih de-nach nafshei, he went into the house
and he saw that Rebbi had died. קרעיה ללבושיה, Kareih le-levushei, he
rent his garments ואהדריה לקרעיה לאחוריה ve-ahadreih le-kareih le-achorei and reversed it,
turned it behind himself, so it wouldn't be like a immediate shock
presumably to the people to the students or to you know to
the sages outside. פתח ואמר Patach ve-amar Bar
Kappara
and then he came out of the house and he said, אראלים
ומצוקים, erelim u-metzukim, angels and sages or righteous people אחזו בארון הקדש.
achazu ba-aron ha-kodesh. This this is a הספד, hesped, you know it's
poetic. Hold on to the holy ark which is, which is presumably
the ארון aron is also the coffin right of Rebbi. The holy
ark, or were holding on to the holy ark. נצחו אראלי את
המצוקים, nitzchu Areilei et haMetzukim,
the angels beat out over the over the over the
righteous ones. ונשבה ארון הקודש, venishbah aron hakodesh,
and the holy ark was taken captive. So, yeah exactly. אמרו ליה,
amru lei, so they said to him, נח נפשיה, nach nafshai, so
what was? Are you saying he died? So אמר להו, amar lehu,
he said to them, אתון קאמריתו, atun kamritu, you said it, ואנא
לא קאמינא,
va'ana
lo kamina, right. You don't want to be impaled by the sword.
Exactly, you don't want to be... there you go, you don't want
to be impaled by the sword. I was thinking about the beginning
of פסחים Pesachim where you're like, מוציא דבה הוא כסיל, motzi dibah
hu k'sil, you're not supposed to say anything bad, but you're right
Michael, it was exactly that. He didn't want to get the sword.
Okay, you said it.
מצוקים, metzukim, the righteous ones?
Like מצוקי ארץ, metzukei eretz, like those that are sort of like
are the foundations of the earth. Okay. ואנא לא קאמינא, va'ana lo
kamina,
I didn't say it. בשעת פטירתו שרבי, bish'at ptirato she'rebbe, when Rebbe
died, at the time of his death, זקף עשר אצבעותיו כלפי מעלה,
zakaf eser etzba'otav klapei ma'alah, he put his ten fingers up to
heaven, אמר, amar, he said, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel olam, Master
of the Universe, גלוי וידוע לפניך שיגעתי בעשר אצבעותי בתורה, galui veyadu'ah
lefanecha she'yagati be'eser etzba'otai batorah, you know that I have like wearied
with my ten fingers in the learning of Torah, I worked my
fingers to the bone, ולא נהניתי אפילו באצבע קטנה, v'lo neheneti afilu
be'etzba ktanah, and I did not derive any benefit from this world
even from a pinky. I know. יהי רצון מלפניך שיהא שלום במנוחתי,
yehi ratzon milfanecha she'yehei shalom bimnuchati, may it be Thy will God
that there will be peace in my finding my resting place. יצאה
בת קול ואמרה, yatzta bat kol v'amrah, a heavenly voice came and
said, יבוא שלום, yavo shalom, they come in peace, ינוחו על משכבותם,
yanuchu al mishkevotam, let them rest on their you know on their
in their beds. Also the גמרא Gemara says ינוחו על משכבותם? yanuchu
al mishkevotam? על משכבך מיבעי ליה, al mishkevcha mi-ba'ei lei, it should
say on your bed, because יבוא yavo means you should come in
peace. So what's ינוחו על משכבותם, yanuchu al mishkevotam, their beds? So
מסייע ליה mesaye'a lei to רבי חייא בר גמדא, Rabbi Chiya bar
Gamda, this supports רבי חייא בר גמדא, Rabbi Chiya bar Gamda, ואמר
רבי חייא בר גמדא, v'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Gamda, not the same
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya we had before, אמר רבי יוסי בר שאול,
amar Rabbi Yose bar Shaul, בשעה שהצדיק נפטר מן העולם, b'sha'ah she'hatzaddik
niftar min ha'olam, when a righteous person passes from the world, אומרים
מלאכי השרת לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, omrei mal'achei hasharet lifnei Hakadosh Baruch
Hu, the angels say to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel olam,
Master of the Universe, צדיק פלוני בא, tzaddik ploni ba, the righteous
person so-and-so is coming. אמר להם, amar lahem, He says to the
angels, יבואו צדיקים, yavo'u tzaddikim, let all the let all the righteous
people in heaven come out, ויצאו לקראתו, v'yeitzu likrato, and come greet
him, ויאמרו לו יבוא בשלום, v'omeru lo yavo veshalom, and say to
him, come in peace. Then after they've greeted him, ינוחו על משכבותם,
yanuchu al mishkevotam, then all the righteous people can go back to
their beds. So the ינוחו על משכבותם yanuchu al mishkevotam are all
the righteous people that are coming out to greet the righteous one
who has died. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, בשעה שצדיק נפטר
מן העולם, b'sha'ah she'tzaddik niftar min ha'olam, when the righteous person passes
from the world, שלוש כיתות של מלאכי השרת יוצאות לקראתו. shalosh kitot
shel mal'achei hasharet yotzot likrato. Three groups of the heavenly angels come
out to greet him. אחת אומרת לו יבוא בשלום, achat omeret lo
yavo veshalom,
come in peace. ואחת אומרת לו הולך נכוחו, ve'achat omeret lo holech
nechucho, go in your righteousness. ואחת אומרת לו יבוא שלום ינוחו על
משכבותם, ve'achat omeret lo yavo shalom yanuchu al mishkevotam,
come in peace and rest on your resting places, presumably saying to
all the other I don't know angels or righteous people. בשעה שרשע
נאבד מן העולם, b'sha'ah she'rasha ne'evad min ha'olam, when the wicked person
is destroyed from the world, שלוש כיתות של מלאכי חבלה יוצאות לקראתו,
shalosh kitot shel mal'achei chabalah yotzot likrato, three groups come out to
greet him. אחת אומרת אין שלום אמר ה' לרשעים, achat omeret Ein
shalom, amar Hashem, la'resha'im, there is no peace, said the Lord, for
the wicked. ואחת אומרת לו למעצבה ישכב, ve'achat omeret lo l'ma'atzevah yishkav,
in anguish you will lie down, in suffering. ואחת אומרת לו רדה
והשכבה את ערלים, ve'achat omeret lo redei vehashkevah et areilim, go down,
lie down with the uncircumcised, so go down I presume to hell.
Now, two points. One is that רבי Rebbe says I never got
any benefit from even the smallest thing, you know there's other גמרות
Gemaras that say רבי Rebbe and אנטונינוס... Antoninus...
exactly, that they had like the you
know these delicacies on their table, him and the you know the
Roman leader. So anyway, so look, it could be going back to
the point before about the difference between a sense of private life
and a public life, that maybe he was necessarily for him to
do that in terms of his role as the נשיא, nasi, but
it does not mean that he really was desirous of those. And
the other thing could be, you know, I think, I mean there's
a lot of discussion about this in you know hashkafic literature, right,
about it doesn't mean that you don't actually
get benefit from this world, right, you have to eat the most
dry, tasteless type of fish. But the question is about whether you're
doing it essentially לשם שמים l'shem shamayim and are you doing it
in some way that's enabling you to serve God better, or are
you doing it, you know, for your sort of own ease. But
yes, it's interesting to try to put those stories together.
It's Torah, not his group. He never took any honoraria for giving
a שיעור. shiur.
Oh, that's interesting. Meaning לא נהניתי lo neheneti from the from the
Torah work I did. I didn't use the Torah like in order
to benefit me. Oh, that's interesting. That's a nice פשט. pshat. Okay.
Right. I mean תוספות, Tosafot, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות
Tosafot doesn't read it that way, but that's a nice פשט. pshat.
תוספות Tosafot says לא נהניתי, lo neheneti, דאמרינן במדרש, d'amrinan b'midrash, עד
שאתה מתפלל שיכנס תורה לתוך גופו, ad she'ata mitpaleil she'yikaneis Torah l'toch
gufo, while you're praying that Torah should go into your body, התפלל
שלא יכנסו מעדנים לתוך גופו. hitpaleil she'lo yikaneis ma'adanim l'toch gufo. Don't
try
don't have delicacies go into your body. So it seems like it's
talking about investing your life in the in the spiritual, not in
the physical pleasures. But I but you that's a nice פשט pshat
too, like you worked your fingers to the bone and you don't
benefit from it, right. So one last point though about this oseph
about the idea of if you remember there were all these stories
about, you know, רבי's Rebbe death, similar because everybody was, you know,
12 months of of of mourning over his death, and similar to
the 12 months. months for a parent and that idea of what
happens when a great תורה Torah sage dies as it's similar to
the death of a parent and so on. Look at this little
תוספות Tosfos back very quickly on ק"ג עמוד ב'. kof gimmel amud
bais. אותו יום שמת רבי בטלה קדושה, Oso yom shemeis Rebbi batla
kedusha, שהיו קוראים לו רבנו הקדוש, she'hayu korim lo Rabbeinu HaKadosh, okay.
והא דתניא בשילהי סוטה משמת רבי בטלה ענוה ויראה, Veha de'tanya bishilei
Sotah mishemeis Rebbi batla anavah ve'yirah, not only holiness but also humility
and fear. יש לומר קדושה בכלל, Yeish lomar kedusha bikhlal, that kedusha's
included, fine. ורב רבי חיים כהן היה אומר, Ve'Rav Rebbi Chaim Kohen
haya omer, note that he was a כהן. Kohen. אלמלא הייתי, Ilmalei
hayisi, were I there, כשנפטר רבנו תם, kesheniftar Rabbeinu Tam, when רבנו
תם Rabbeinu Tam had died, הייתי מיטמא לו, hayisi mitamei lo, I
would have made myself impure for him as a כהן, Kohen, he's
saying. דבטלה קדושה דכאמר הכא היינו קדושת כהונה, De'batla kedusha de'ka'amar hacha
hinu kedushas kehuna, it would be like there would be no laws
of כהונה. kehuna. Everybody was, it'd be like an immediate relative dies
and even כהנים Kohanim would become טמא tamei to him, okay? וכן
מוכח מדקאמר אותו יום,
Vekhein mochiach
midka'amar oso yom, משמע אותו יום
דווקא ותו לא.
mashma oso yom
davka ve'su lo.
It didn't mean that there was no more קדושה kedusha in the
world, it meant for that day there was no קדושה, kedusha, even
כהנים Kohanim would become טמא. tamei. ובהדיא אמרו בירושלמי דברכות פרק מי
שמתו, Uvehedya amru biYerushalmi de'Berachos perek mi shemeiso, דכשמת רבי אמרו אין
כהונה היום, de'keshemeis Rebbi amru ein kehuna hayom,
right? And then תוספות Tosfos pulls back, ונראה לרבי, Venireh le'Rebbi, not
Rebbi Rebbi, the author of תוספות, Tosfos, דכמדומה לרבי דהתם מיירי בטומאת
בית הפרס דרבנן, de'chimduma le'Rebbi de'hasam mairi betumas beis hapras de'Rabbanan, טומאת
דאורייתא לא. tumas de'Oraisa lo.
He's a little bit reluctant to say it by a דאורייתא. de'Oraisa.
The story was when the רב"ד Raavad died, the כהנים Kohanim of
פוסקייר, Posquières, I believe it was, basically were מיטמא mitamei to bury
him. So it's yeah, that's recorded in Twersky's book on the רב"ד.
Raavad. So there actually was this idea that when like the גדול
הדור gadol hador dies, even the כהנים Kohanim are מיטמא. mitamei. So
very interesting. What? Oh,
yeah, it was more about the idea of a גדול הדור, gadol
hador, like for the רבי, Rebbi, you know, for all of כלל
ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Okay, let's take a look at the next משנה
mishnah ק"ד עמוד א'. kof daled amud aleph. כל זמן שהיא בבית
אביה, Kol zman she'hi be'veis aviha,
as long as the widow is in her father's house, גובה כתובתה
לעולם, gova kesuvasa le'olam,
she can collect her כתובה kesuvah forever, right? It's a payment that's
owed to her, so even if she takes her time collecting it,
she can whenever she wants, she can collect it. כל זמן שהיא
בבית בעלה, Kol zman she'hi be'veis ba'ala, but if she's living in
her deceased husband's house and being supported by the estate, גובה כתובתה
עד עשרים וחמש שנים, gova kesuvasa ad esrim ve'chamesh shanim, only 25
years. שיש בעשרים וחמש שנים שתעשה טובה כנגד כתובתה, She'yeish be'esrim ve'chamesh
shanim she'ta'aseh tovah keneged kesuvasa, דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rebbi Meir,
because over the course of 25 years she'll basically the small little
benefits she'll have gotten off of the estate that maybe weren't strictly
owed to her. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says maybe she'll give some
gifts, you know, use some money, some types of things or whatever,
she'll have ultimately collected her כתובה kesuvah payment over the course of
that period of time, even you know just by little things that
are given to her that she can take which aren't strictly owed
to her. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim,
but the sages say, כל זמן שהיא בבית בעלה, kol zman she'hi
be'veis ba'ala, the opposite, while she's in her husband's house, גובה כתובתה
לעולם, gova kesuvasa le'olam, she could always collect it. כל זמן שהיא
בבית אביה, Kol zman she'hi be'veis aviha, when she's in her father's
house, גובה כתובתה עד עשרים וחמש שנים, gova kesuvasa ad esrim ve'chamesh
shanim, 25 years. Because it's assumed after 25 years if you haven't
collected it in 25 years you're מוחל. mochel. If that's true, why
don't we say the same if she's in her husband's house? Because
then the reason she hasn't asked for it in 25 years is
not because she's מוחלת, mocheles, but she's like a little bit embarrassed
to ask for it. Here are the heirs, they're putting her up,
they're paying her food bills, and so on, and all of a
sudden she's going to sort of say pay me up my כתובה?
kesuvah? So there her silence is not interpreted as a מחילה, mechila,
but if she's living apart from them and she hasn't done anything
about it in 25 years then it's considered to be a מחילה.
mechila. One minute. מתה, Meisa, now let's say she dies within the
25 years, יורשיה מזכירים כתובתה עד עשרים וחמש שנים. yoresheha mazkirim kesuvasa
ad esrim ve'chamesh shanim.
So the 25 years, you know, continues through the life of the
heirs. So she died after 10 years, the heirs have 15 years
to demand the כתובה, kesuvah, and if they don't demand it within
the next 15 years then that'll be effectively a מחילה. mechila. Yes,
Oved?
The husband dies, so her whole do the פירות peiros of her
whole holdings that he had been using go then back to her?
As soon as the husband dies, yes, then she starts... yes.
So she's got that as a source of income as well.
That is true, if she had those holdings as נכסי מלוג, nichsei
melog, then she starts collecting the פירות, peiros, that is correct.
So the פירות peiros don't go then to the heirs.
That is correct, that is correct. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye le'Rav Yosef,
so now this is within רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir's idea that over
the 25 years eventually if she's hanging around in her husband's house
eventually you know little things adding up you know she'll have gotten
her כתובה kesuvah payment, her כתובה kesuvah payment will have all added
up. You know like
haven't you heard these stories about the guy that basically you know
when the banks you know when it figures out how much interest
it pays people right it rounds off to the nearest penny and
the bank keeps the difference and one guy basically like basically managed
to
get
it so that all those rounding errors, Office
Space, Superman III?
I don't really... anyway fine anyway right anyway anyway it adds up
to like millions of dollars all those little portions of pennies you
know the unpaid amount on a credit card.
There you go. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye le'Rav
Yosef, I don't get it he said ענייה שבישראל, Aniya she'beYisrael,
if you have this poor woman in you know the poorest woman
in Israel Israel and her כתובה kesubah is the bare minimum, עד
עשרים וחמש שנים, ad esrim v'chamesh shanim, it takes 25 years for
her כתובה kesubah to be paid off living in her husband's house,
in her dead husband's house. ומרתא בת בייתוס, Marta Bas Baisos, מרתא
בת בייתוס Marta Bas Baisos you might remember her from before, extremely
wealthy, so her כתובה kesubah must have been hundreds of thousands of
dollars. It wasn't the bare 100 and 200. עד עשרים וחמש שנים,
ad esrim v'chamesh shanim, in 25 years that amount is going to
get paid off? So the Gemara says: אמר ליה, amar lei, yes,
לפום גמלא שיחנא, lifum gamla shichna, based on the camel so is
the burden. If she's sitting around her dead husband's house, she's not
getting a few pennies here and a few pennies there. Every now
and then she buys herself a necklace or whatever, you know, to
buy a Ferrari, goes to the opera, so eventually it does add
up. One minute. איבעיא להו, iba'u lehu, they asked: לרבי מאיר מהו
שתשלש? l'Rabbi Meir mahu she'tishales? According to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, do
you pro-rate it? Let's say after 10 years, if the idea is
that slowly, slowly she's been getting little benefits along the way, so
maybe after
12 and a half years half of her כתובה kesubah should be
assumed to be paid off, and after six years a quarter of
her כתובה, kesubah, right? Why is it from zero to 100? The
idea is a little little by little she's getting little benefits that
should be counted up against her כתובה. kesubah. Okay, you had a
question, Joey?
מרתא בת בייתוס Marta Bas Baisos did not live 25 years after
him.
All right, that doesn't matter. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף. amar lei
Abaye l'Rav Yosef. Now, מכדי ומי כל זמן. michdi umi kol zman.
Now the Rabbis say the opposite. It's not that we count little
things that she's getting, that is presumably
מחילה mechila on the part of the heirs, it's the opposite, that
if she's living apart and she doesn't ask for it for 25
years, then she's considered to have been מוחל. mochel. אמר ליה אביי
לרב יוסף amar lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef ובעא מיניה דרב יוסף, u'vaya
minei d'Rav Yosef, I don't get it. אתאי קודם שקיעת החמה, atai
kodem shekias hachama, she came before sunset on the end of the
last day of 25 years, גובה כתובתה, govi kesubasau, she collects her
full כתובה. kesubah. ולאחר שקיעת החמה, v'achar shekias hachama, she came one
minute after sunset, לא גביא, lo gavya, she gets nothing?
So בהא פורתא אחילתא, be-hai pursak yalto, that little bit
she waives her כתובה? kesubah? אמר ליה, amar lei, אין, in, yes.
כל מדות חכמים כן הוא, kol middos chachamim kein hu, this is
the way of the
Sages' amounts. You have to create some limit, you have to create
some definition. בארבעים סאה טובל, b'arba'im se'ah tovel,
with 40 סאה se'ah you can go into the mikvah if he
has that amount of water. בארבעים סאה חסר קורטוב, b'arba'im se'ah chasar
kurtov, if it's missing a symbol of water, אינו יכול לטבול בהן.
eino yachol litbol bahen. All right. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב:
amar Rav Yehuda
amar
Rav: העיד רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי לפני רבי, he'id Rabbi Yishmael b'Rebbi
Yosi lifnei Rebbi, רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael b'Rebbi Yosi testified
in front of רבי, Rebbi, שאמר משום אביו, she'amar mishum aviv, said
in the name of his father: לא שנו אלא שאין שטר כתובה
יוצא מתחת ידה. lo shanu ela she-ein shtar kesubah yotzei mitachas yadah.
When is it that we assume there's מחילה? mechila? Only if she's
not carrying on to the IOU document, she doesn't have the כתובה
kesubah document in her hand. Then you could say it's only an
oral debt and she hasn't been asking for it, she's just letting
it go by the wayside. But as long as she's holding on
to the document, to the שטר, shtar, so okay, she's not asking
for it because she's got the document, she can use it whenever
she wants. You can't interpret a מחילה mechila there. אבל שטר כתובה
יוצא מתחת ידה, גובה כתובתה לעולם, Aval shtar kesubah yotzei mitachat yadah
gova kesubatah l'olam,
she could always collect it. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar אמר, amar, רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar disagrees, he says: אפילו שטר כתובה יוצא מתחת ידה
אינו גובה אלא עד עשרים וחמש שנים. afilu shtar kesubah yotzei mitachas
yadah eino govei ela ad esrim v'chamesh shanim. No, even if she's
holding on to the כתובה, kesubah, she only has 25 years.
Okay, as long as it's not over 25.
Right. מתיב רב ששת, masiv Rav Sheshes, now רב ששת Rav Sheshes
asked: בעל חוב גובה שלא בהזכרה. ba'al chov gova she-lo b'hazkarah. A
בעל חוב ba'al chov can collect it anytime without ever having to
make an announcement and say I'm still planning on collecting. Meaning we
never interpret that there's ever any מחילה mechila if it's a normal
creditor.
Only by a widow would we interpret that. היכי דמי? heichi dami?
What's the case? אי דלא נקט שטר, iy d'lo nakat shtar,
if he's not holding on to a שטר, shtar, במאי גבי? b'mai
govei? How is he collecting anyway? אלא דנקט שטר, ela d'nakat shtar,
it must be that he has a שטר. shtar. ובעל חוב הוא
דלא הזכרה ליה, u'ba'al chov hu d'lo hazkara lei, and it's the
בעל חוב ba'al chov that we say that he never, that we
never assume that he's מוחל, mochel, that he waives it. And therefore
he can collect forever even with a שטר, shtar, and but with
a שטר. shtar. הא אלמנה אחילתא, ha almanah achilta,
the widow,
she does waive it even though she's got a שטר? shtar? So
the question was like what type of question was that? The same
way there could be two scenarios of a widow collecting with or
without a שטר, shtar, there could be two scenarios of a בעל
חוב. ba'al chov. הוא מתיב לה והוא מפרק לה, hu masiv lah
v'hu m'farek lah, he asked and he answered: לעולם דלא נקט שטר,
l'olam d'lo nakat shtar, yeah, by the בעל חוב ba'al chov maybe
we're talking also without a שטר. shtar. והכא במאי עסקינן דחייב מודה,
v'hacha b'mai askinan d'chayiv modeh, we're talking about that the other side,
the debtor, concedes, admits that he owes the money. The same way
we could imagine a scenario that the woman collects without a שטר,
shtar, we could imagine a scenario the בעל חוב. ba'al chov. Now
that answer seems obvious. Why did the Gemara assume the בעל חוב
ba'al chov has to have a שטר? shtar? Because if you'll remember,
the widow doesn't need a שטר shtar to prove she's owed the
money. Every widow is owed that money, it's תנאי בית דין. t'nai
beis din. All she has to prove is that her husband is
dead. So it's easier to imagine a scenario where the woman can
prove that she's owed the money without a שטר, shtar, she just
proves that her husband is dead. Whereas a בעל חוב, ba'al chov,
if he doesn't have a שטר, shtar, he can't prove it. So
it's a much less likely scenario he's going to be able to
collect. And nevertheless the Gemara says okay, but we could still imagine
a case where the other side admits it and that he is
able to collect. That's where there will be, where we're comparing, but
actually if there is a שטר, Shtar, even a widow can always
collect. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואמר רבי אילא
שנוין גרושה. V'amar Rabbi Ila shonin gerusha. Doesn't Rabbi אילא Ila say
that we teach a גרושה gerusha הרי היא כבעל חוב? harei hi
k'ba'al chov? She's like a בעל חוב ba'al chov because a גרושה
gerusha is never מוחל, mochel, right? It's not that they, you know,
they were obviously antagonistic or they were divorced. She has no lost
love, so therefore she's never going to be מוחל. mochel. It's one
thing to say that, you know, in a case of a widow
she's מוחל mochel the husband's estate, the heirs, but a גרושה gerusha
isn't מוחל mochel and she can always collect. היכי דמי? Heichi dami?
What's the case? דאי לא נקט כתובה במאי גביא? D'ei lo nakat
kesubah b'mai gavya? If she's not holding onto a כתובה, kesubah, how
is she collecting? אלא לאו דנקט כתובה? Ella lav d'nakat kesubah? She
must be holding onto a כתובה. kesubah. וגרושה היא דלא בת מחילה
היא. V'gerusha hi d'lo bat mechila hi. It's the גרושה gerusha who
does not, who isn't מוחל. mochel. הא אלמנה, Ha almanah, but a
widow, אחילתא, achilta, she does,
she is מוחל mochel even though she's holding onto a שטר. Shtar.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכא נמי כשחייב מודה, Hacha nami
k'shechayav modeh, even though it's a case of a divorced, you know,
of a divorced couple and you might think that the other side
would be less likely to admit it is debt, we can still
imagine that's the case. So we're still going to try to say
that the case where there's מחילה mechila by the אלמנה almanah is
only when there's no שטר. Shtar. Maybe when there's שטר Shtar there
is no מחילה. mechila. Okay, so we really haven't proven one way
or the other. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק תני רב יהודה בר
קזא במתניסא דבי בר קזא. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak tani Rav
Yehuda bar Kaza b'matnisa d'bei bar Kaza. So Rabbi Yehuda bar Kaza
teaches in
the ברייתות braitas of בי בר קזא. Bei bar Kaza. תבעה כתובתה,
Tavah kesubatah, if she demands her כתובה, kesubah, הרי היא כבתחילה. harei
hi k'batchila. The clock starts again. Once she comes to court and
registers I want to collect my כתובה, kesubah, she's got another 25
years, you know, to before, before it's considered a מחילה. mechila. All
right? ואי היתה כתובה, V'im hayta kesubah, she doesn't have to collect
her כתובה kesubah within 25 years. She just has to ask for
it to be paid and then she's got another 25 years from
that point before having to ask for it again.
No, I understand, but when she asks for it, doesn't she have
to get it?
I mean, why does she have to wait 25 years? No, she's
made it clear that she's not מוחל. mochel. There has to pass
25 years of silence in order to be interpreted as מחילה. mechila.
No, but I'm trying to understand why if she asked for her
כתובה, kesubah, then why didn't she get it?
I don't know, because they said we don't have the money, we
need to go ahead and sell some stuff, whatever. Okay, we'll come
back to court next week and then she let it slide for
another 25 years. All right? ואי היתה כתובה יוצאת מתחת ידה, V'im
hayta kesubah yotzeit mitachat yadah,
and if she actually is holding onto the שטר כתובה, Shtar kesubah,
גובה כתובתה לעולם. govi kesubasau l'olam, So again, you see
the pushback against the משנה.
Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah has this idea that there's a מחילה mechila
after 25 years, but now we're limiting it. Number one is she
just has to ask for it once and the clock starts again,
and number two, as long as she's holding onto the כתובה, kesubah,
there's no מחילה mechila at all. No. שלח ליה רב נחמן בר
רב חסדא לרב נחמן בר יעקב. Shelach lei Rav Nachman bar Rav
Chisda l'Rav Nachman bar Yaakov. ילמדנו רבנו, Yilamdenu rabbeinu, our master, sorry,
but our master teacher. כששטר כתובה יוצא מתחת ידה מחלוקת, K'shtar kesubah
yotzei mitachat yadah machloket,
is the debate when she's holding onto the שטר כתובה Shtar kesubah
או כשאין שטר כתובה יוצא מתחת ידה? o k'she'ein shtar kesubah yotzei
mitachat yadah? Or is the debate when she's not holding onto the
כתובה? kesubah? והלכה כדברי מי? V'halacha k'divrei mi? Who is the law
like? שלח ליה, Shelach lei, he sent back, בשאין שטר כתובה יוצא
מתחת ידה מחלוקת. B'she'ein shtar kesubah yotzei mitachat yadah machloket.
The debate is if not holding onto the כתובה. kesubah. With the
כתובה kesubah there's never מחילה. mechila. אבל שטר כתובה יוצא מתחת ידה
aval shtar kesubah yotzei mitachas yadah, גובה כתובתה לעולם, gova kesubatah l'olam.
number one. And number two, when she's not holding onto the כתובה,
kesubah, והלכה כדברי חכמים, v'halacha k'divrei chachamim,
we rule like the חכמים chachamim that it's an issue of being
מוחל, mochel, and it's when she's in her father's house, but when
she's in her husband's house, there's never מחילה, mechila, which is again
to her interest because when she's in, the other argument would be
that when she's in her husband's house it's slowly being paid off.
That we reject. כי אתא רב דימי, Ki ata Rav Dimi, when
Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר רבי שמעון בן
פזי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא. Amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Pazi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi mishum bar Kappara. לא שנו
אלא מנה מאתיים. Lo shanu ella maneh matayim. This idea that there's
מחילה, mechila, again, we keep on cutting and cutting and cutting where
she would be forfeiting her rights. This idea that there's מחילה mechila
is only the base 100 and 200. אבל תוספת יש לה, Aval
tosefet yesh lah, any additional amount she has. That's a gift. And
since it's a gift, we don't assume that if I've given you
a gift that there would ever be מחילה. mechila. So the base
moral obligation you could say, you know, somehow the husband and wife
and she's a widow and the heirs or whatever, maybe that they
were, she was מוחל mochel because of the nature of the marriage.
But the תוספת, tosefet, that's seen as a straight gift and we
don't interpret any מחילה mechila in that context. ורבי אבהו אמר רבי
יוחנן אפילו תוספת אין לה. V'Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Yochanan afilu tosefet
ein lah. No, even the תוספת tosefet would be considered to be
waived after 25 years. דאמר רבי אייבו אמר רבי ינאי, D'amar Rabbi
Aibu amar Rabbi Yannai, תנאי כתובה ככתובה דמי. Tnai kesubah k'kesubah dami.
We treat the other position, the other elements of the כתובה kesubah
like the base כתובה. kesubah. איתמר נמי, Itmar nami, it was also
taught. אמר רבי אבא אמר רב הונא אמר רב. Amar Rabbi Abba
amar Rav Huna amar Rav. לא שנו אלא מנה מאתיים. Lo shanu
ella maneh matayim. The idea that the amount could be waived is
only the base 100 and 200, אבל תוספת יש לה, aval tosefet
yesh lah, she still has the additional. אמר רבי אבא לרב הונא,
Amar Rabbi Abba l'Rav Huna, אמר רב הכי? Amar Rav hachi?
Did Rav really say this, that the, that the תוספת tosefet she
still has? אמר ליה אשתוקין קאמרת או אשקיין קאמרת? Amar lei ashtukin
kaamart o ashkayin kaamart? When you're challenging me did Rav really say
this, is it because you're trying to silence me, meaning because you
don't agree with it, אשתוקין, ashtukin, or is it אשקיין, ashkayin, or
you'd like to take me out for a drink, which would mean
you'd, you like the idea, you like the פסק psak and you
want to make sure that Rav really said it? אמר ליה אשתוקין
קאמינא. Amar lei ashtukin kamina. No, I want to silence you, meaning
I don't agree with that idea. Okay, fine, let's read a bit.
Let's read a little bit more. חמתיה דרבי חייא אריכא, Chamsei d'Rabbi
Chiya Aricha, the mother-in-law of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya the long one—different
רבי חייאs—that Rabbi Chiya was his name, רבי חייא אריכא. Rabbi Chiya
Aricha. איתתא דאחוה
הוי. Itas d'achua havei. His mother-in-law was his brother's wife. And his
brother died, so he was the heir, surviving heir, so he inherited
his brother's estate. And now he had to support his mother-in-law, which
is his brother's widow, right, off of his brother's estate. Okay, so
now, איתתא דאחוה הוי, Itas d'achua havei, דאלמנתא דבי אבא הוי, d'almanta
d'bevei abba havei,
and she was living in her father's house. So there's going to
be the 25-year question. וזנא עשרין וחמש שנין, V'zana esrim v'chamisha shanim,
and he paid her, you know, paid her food bill for 25
years. בבי נשא, Bevei nasha, when she was living in—בבי נשא bevei
nasha as opposed to her husband's house. The women's house, or it's
a question what the word means, but basically when she was living
with her father. וסוף אמרה ליה הב לי מזוני, V'sof amra lei
hav li mezonei, and after—now we hadn't discussed this, but after 25
years when she's מוחל, mochel, is she מוחל mochel only the base
or—we discussed base and תוספת, tosefet, how about continuing מזונות? mezonot? Can
she get that to be paid after 25 years? So after 25
years she said, 'Keep on paying my food bill.' אמרה ליה, Amra
lei, 'לית לך מזוני,' Leis lach mezonei, no, you don't have any
מזוני mezonei anymore, 25 years has been up. 'הב לי כתובה, Hav
li ktuvah, give me my כתובה.' ktuvah. אמר לה, Amar lah, 'לא
מזוני אית לך ולא כתובה אית לך,' Lo mezonei is lach v'lo
ktuvah is lach, you don't have anything. Now you wonder what's his
wife going to say? Because this is also his wife's mother. Anyway,
okay. So he said you don't get anything. תביעתא לדינא קמיה דרבה
בר שילא. Taviesay l'dina kammai d'Rabba bar Shila. So she brought him
to a judgment in front of רבה בר שילא. Rabba bar Shila.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said to him, 'אימא לי איזי
גופא דעובדא היכי הוה, Eima li eezi gufa d'uvda heichi hava, tell
me in truth what the story was.' אמר ליה, Amar lei, 'זנתה
עשרין וחמש שנין, Zanisa esrim v'chamisha shanim,
I supported her for 25 years.' בבי נשא, Bevei nasha, in her
father's house. בחיי דמר, Bechaiei d'mar, and in the life of the
master I will tell you how good of care I took for
her. דאכתפאי אייתי ליה, D'akatafei aiteilei, I brought her the food on
my very shoulder. I drove the food over to her every single
day or every single week. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said, 'Oh,
דבי אמות טעמא מאי אמרו רבנן, d'vei emos ta'ama mai amru rabanan,
why did the rabbis say that כל זמן שהיא בבית בעלה גובה
כתובתה לעולם, kol zman she'hi bevei ba'al govah ktuvatah l'olam, that when
she's in her husband's house it's never considered to waive her rights?
It's only a waiving of rights when it's in the father's house.
דאמרינן משום כיסופא הוא דלא תבעה, D'amrinan mishum kissufa hu d'lo tavah,
because we say the fact that she hasn't asked from the heirs
in 25 years is not that she's waiving her rights, she's embarrassed
to ask it because she's been around the heirs the whole time
and they've been taking good care of her. And that's why she's
been quiet. הכא נמי, Hacha nami, here because you took such good
care of her, so משום כיסופא הוא דלא תבעה, mishum kissufa hu
d'lo tavah, she didn't demand it in 25 years because she was
embarrassed because you were taking such good care of her. Pretty much
exactly. But you don't... it's not considered a waiver. זיל הב לה,
Zil havlah, go pay her. ולא אשגח, V'la ashgach,
he didn't pay attention. כתב לה אדרכתא אנכסי, Katav lah adrachta anichsei,
so he wrote out a judgment against his property that now she
can go and seize the property. אתא לקמיה דרבא, Asa l'kammei d'Rava,
came in front of רבא. Rava. אמר ליה, Amar lei, 'חזי מר
היכי דנין? Chazi mar heichi danyin? Do you see what they did
to me? He wrote this seizure of my property.' אמר ליה, Amar
lei, 'שפיר דנך, Shappir duncha, yeah, that was a good judgment. You
have to keep on paying her.' אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so she said to him, 'אי הכי ניזיל ונהדר
לי פירא, Ee hachi neizil v'neihadar lei peira, so now that she
has won, now she says, hey, she's got the upper
hand, ניזיל ונהדר לי פירא, neizil v'neihadar lei peira, let's go have
him pay back the fruit, מההוא יומא עד האידנא, mi'hahu yoma ad
idna, from the time he wrote the seizure document until now.' I
was entitled to that piece of property. He snuck it out. Give
me the fruit that's come from that piece of property for the
last three months while he hasn't yet paid up that piece of
property. אמר לה, Amar lah, 'אחוי לי אדרכתיך, Achvi li adrachtich, show
me the document.' Now we see it's always a bad thing to
give too much information. חזיא, Chazya, so she showed רבא. Rava. ולא
הוה כתיב בה, V'lo hava katav bah, that it was not written
in the document, the seizure document, ואשתמודענא דנכסי דמיתנא אינון, v'ishtemodana d'nichsei
d'misna inun, and it's known to us that these properties belong to
the deceased. Okay, the her husband who had died, that's the one
she has rights to seize. אמר לה, Amar lah, he said to
her, 'אדרכתא לא שפיר כתיבא, Adrachta la shappir ktiva, there's a technical
problem in the seizure document because the seizure document is only good
if it identifies the property that you have a right to. And
you don't have the rights to... you only have the rights to
your dead husband's property to seize for the support.
As a punishment that she would get his property?
No. אמר ליה, Amar lei, she said to him, 'תיזיל אדרכתא, Teizil
adrachta, forget about the seizure document. אסר, Asar, I won't ask for
the fruit from the time of the document. לא אשאל פירא מיומא
דאדרכתא. Lo esha peira mi'yoma d'rachta. אלא מיומא דשלמו ימי אכרזתא, Ela
mi'yoma d'shaleimu yemei achrazta, but from the time that remember the whole
auction process was over and then I actually—forgetting even the document. So
I don't own it from the time the document was written, but
I should own it from the time that the auction was over
and that time it's my property and it was sold or whatever,
you know, and then I should actually be able to collect it
and collect the פירות peirot עד השתא, ad hasha, until now.' אמר
לה, Amar lah, 'הני מילי היכא דלא כתיב טעותא באדרכתא, Hani milei
heicha d'lo ktiv tauta b'adrachta, when is it that you're considered to
own it after the auction process? If there has not been an
error in the seizure document. אבל היכא דכתיב טעותא באדרכתא לית לן
בה, Aval heicha d'ktiv tauta b'adrachta leis lan bah, when there's an
error in the seizure document then the whole thing is off. is
a technicality and whatever and you only own it when you actually
take possession at no earlier stage. אמר ליה *Amar lei* והא איהו
דאמר *veha ihu d'amar* you're the one that says אחריות טעות סופר
הוא *achrayus ta'us sofer hu* that any mistake in the document is
seen as just like a slip-up and it doesn't really change the
basic fundamental nature of the document. אמר רבא *Amar Rava* בהא לא
מצי למימר טעות סופר הוא *beha lo matzi lemeimar ta'us sofer hu*.
No, this you cannot just say is a simple oversight
דהא חזינא דבשיבנא טעי *deha chazina devshivna ta'ei* because here there really
was an error. It wasn't just he forgot to write it. He
actually made a real mistake. מעיקרא הוא סבר הא והא דידיה הוא
*me'ikara hu savar ha veha didey hu*. He said look all the
property is owned by you know your son-in-law here, the dead person's
brother. מאי מהאי ומאי מהאי *mai mehai u-mai mehai*? What does it
make if she seizes you know her dead husband's estate, what does
it make if she seizes her son-in-law's estate? Either way he's got
to pay. So he actually made an error by not identifying the
property. He actually thought you were entitled to any of the property.
But it's not true. No, you're not entitled to any of the
property. זימנין דאזיל ומשבח להו *zimnin de'azil u-meshabbach lehu* if you were
to take the property that was not your dead husband's, you would
go and improve it והוו להו נכסי *vehavu lehu nichsei* and your
dead husband's would depreciate in value. And then after a while he
would come to the court and say, your son-in-law, ואמר לה שקול
דידך והב לי דידי *ve'amar lah shakul didach vehav li didi* take
the property that's your dead husband's and give me my property. So
the reality is even though he has to pay you, you're not
entitled to any of his property. You're only entitled to the one
that belonged to your dead husband ואתי לאפוקי לעז אבית דינא *ve'asi
le'afokei la'az abei dina* and it would then raise questions about the
beis din in order that they're not doing the right thing. Okay.
That is as far as we finish it. חזק וברוך *Chazak u'baruch*.
So the bottom line is he had to pay her even after
the 25 years. Okay. And we will end with that. All right.
We went a little over.
So funny, right, so he at some point he still continued to
pay some מזונות *mezonos* and the כתובה *kesubah* whatever, right? Just a
question about that interim period.
Exactly.
Take a look and see how much time we want for the
effectively the day one is very very long.